<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Marcin Kwiatkowski's Blog]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Blog about software engineering.]]></description>
        <link>https://frodigo.com</link>
        <image>
            <url>https://frodigo.com/favicon-32.png</url>
            <title>Marcin Kwiatkowski&apos;s Blog</title>
            <link>https://frodigo.com</link>
        </image>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Mon, 31 Mar 2025 17:08:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://frodigo.com/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Mon, 31 Mar 2025 17:08:00 GMT</pubDate>
        <language><![CDATA[en]]></language>
        <ttl>60</ttl>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[About]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<h2>Who I am</h2>
<h3>TLDR: Software Engineer</h3>
<p>![[marcin_kwiatkowski2025.jpeg]]</p>
<p>Hi! I am Marcin Kwiatkowski!</p>
<p>I am a <strong>software engineer</strong>.</p>
<p>I <strong>solve problems</strong> with code. I write this code from Poland and I love writing code. ...]]></description>
            <link>https://frodigo.com/About</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://frodigo.com/About</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>Who I am</h2>
<h3>TLDR: Software Engineer</h3>
<p>![[marcin_kwiatkowski2025.jpeg]]</p>
<p>Hi! I am Marcin Kwiatkowski!</p>
<p>I am a <strong>software engineer</strong>.</p>
<p>I <strong>solve problems</strong> with code. I write this code from Poland and I love writing code. Why? Because I feel that I can help to <strong>solve</strong> some big <strong>problems</strong> by just <strong>writing</strong> some <strong>code</strong>.</p>
<p>15 years ago I was roofing houses, and I don&#39;t really know what pushed me to engineering. <em>Anyway, I am not complaining about this.</em></p>
<p>Currently, in most of my time I am writing code for <strong>Docplanner</strong> and we make health care more human together.</p>
<p>I write this code in <strong>C#</strong> and <strong>Vue.js.</strong> But in the past I wrote code in JavaScript, <strong>PHP</strong>, <strong>React</strong>, <strong>Node.js</strong> and even in <strong>Terraform</strong>.</p>
<p>When I don&#39;t write code, I am writing <strong>articles</strong>. You can see them here on <strong>my blog</strong> and on the Medium.</p>
<p>When I don&#39;t write code, or articles and I force myself to not using computer, I am probably watching my favorite football (<strong>soccer</strong>) team, playing games or <strong>running</strong>. Typically I do these with my lovely <strong>family</strong>.</p>
<p>When I am running I am thinking about code. This is just my way of relaxing. Cringe? Maybe. Sometimes when I am running I dream about having a <strong>classic car</strong> in my garage.</p>
<pre><code class="language-mermaid">mindmap
  root((Me))
    Professional
      Software Engineer
        C#
        Vue.js
        React
        Node.js
        Google Cloud
        Terraform
        JavaScript
      Writing
        Medium
            Stories
        Blog
            Technical articles
            Tutorials
    Personal
      Father
      Husband
      Soccer fan
      Runner
      Gamer
      Reader
      Classic Cars fan
    Projects
      Docplanner
        Healthcare
            Noa Notes
      Open Source
        GitHub &quot;Garage&quot;
          Experiments
          Tools
          Learnings
          Proof of concepts
</code></pre>
<h2>My Philosophy</h2>
<h3>I <del>am</del> want to be a <del>slow</del>free person</h3>
<h4>I don&#39;t want to be a racer in a rat race</h4>
<p>I enjoy new technologies and I am open to learn new things. The learner skill is my first one from the Gallup Clifton Strengths Assessment.</p>
<p>This is so nice to be able to learn new things fast, but there is a dark side of it. Learning just for learning. I realized that I was jumping from one thing to another.</p>
<p>I wanted to be fast, to be better, to prove something to someone. I was not able to focus on one thing for a long time and enjoy it.</p>
<p>Many times I felt that I felt control and I did things like on autopilot. I learned from this. This is rat race and I don&#39;t want to be part of it.</p>
<p>What I am trying to do now is to be a free person.</p>
<ul>
<li>do not accept every new thing that is offered to me</li>
<li>do not believe immediately that XYZ is the thing that will change my life</li>
<li>do not make decisions based on fear of missing out</li>
</ul>
<p>Think slower, be free, avoid autopilot. This is my philosophy I am trying to follow.</p>
<hr>
<h2>How I started</h2>
<p>My first job was about going to shop to buy a beer for my boss.</p>
<h3>The roofer</h3>
<p>I started as a manual worker. In the beginning I was responsible for cleaning the building. Another thing was buying beer for a stuff and move heavy things from one place to another.</p>
<p>After one year I was able to move to the next step and I was able to lay roof tiles.</p>
<p>After a few years I started to be an independent roofer. In addition to roof tiles, I also knew how to install gutters, install roof windows, and do sheet metal work. I became a specialist and even got an assistant.</p>
<h3>The drift</h3>
<p>I liked that job because I was able to create something (roofs) and I felt that this is important job. I worked for people who wanted to have a roof over their heads.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, In Poland this job is not well paid and also it was physically difficult. Hot in summer, Cold in winter. Moreover, many employees there were alcoholics. It was not good environment to be.</p>
<p>I started studying computer science and after 3 years I was able to get a job as a frontend developer.</p>
<hr>
<h2>Me After 10 years</h2>
<p>What a surprise, after years of learning how to code, I ended up leading a team of developers where I needed such different skills that I have had.</p>
<h3>The full-stack developer</h3>
<p>In May 2013 I started to work as a front-end developer at Chop-Chop.org. My job was to convert PSD files to working websites.</p>
<p>After ~ 1 year I joined to a team of Magento developers and started to work on Magento 1.9.x projects and PHP backend.</p>
<p>My next step was to join a Divante - Polish software house where I was able to work with Magento 2.x and create some shops for big Polish companies.</p>
<h3>The tech leader</h3>
<p>After 2.5 years I became the technical leader of the Magento frontend team.</p>
<p>In 2020, I joined to a Gorilla Group where I was able to work with international team and develop shops for clients from US market. Also at that time I started contributing to the Magento platform and to the PWA Studio - modern storefront for Magento 2.</p>
<p>In 2021, I was invited to join to the Vuestorefront as a tech leader. I was responsible for leading the team and project.</p>
<h3>The software engineer</h3>
<p>After three years of being a tech leader I felt like I don&#39;t do what I really want to do. Guess what? I missed coding. I missed writing code. I missed creating something from scratch.</p>
<p>I found a new job at Docplanner where I am able to write code again and create new features I am working with C# and Vue.js.</p>
<p>I like the Docplanner culture and the mission which is about making healthcare more human.</p>
<hr>
<h2>Me now and future me</h2>
<p>I want to focus on the engineering and turn into the AI engineer.</p>
<h3>The AI engineer</h3>
<p>Recently I experimented with AI and I want to go deeper into this area. Maybe transition from the fullstack developer to the AI engineer is a next turn on my road.</p>
<p>Also I back to school! I started my master&#39;s degree in artificial intelligence and machine learning.</p>
<p>Next two years I will be learning a lot of new things which I will share here.</p>
<h3>The educator</h3>
<p>After few years of drifting I want to go back to the roots and help others to learn.</p>
<p>Because I like learning and I like writing I want to try to connect these two activities into one and share my knowledge with others.</p>
<h3>The Writer</h3>
<p>Writing a book is a big challenge, isn&#39;t it? The value of books in the AI area decreases every day.</p>
<p>But I hope books will survive and will be valuable for a long time.</p>
<hr>
<h2>My Services</h2>
<ul>
<li>Technical Mentoring</li>
<li>Architecture Consulting</li>
<li>Career Development Planning</li>
<li>Technical Content Creation</li>
<li>Software engineering</li>
</ul>
<p>[[Contact|Hire me]]</p>
]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Blog]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>Welcome in my blog. Below I listed all my articles from newest to oldest. You can also explore the blog using sidebar navigation. Enjoy!</p>
<h2>Software Architecture</h2>
<ul>
<li>[[Monolith vs Microservices - Pros and Cons and How to Approach Transformation]]</li>
<li>[[Hexa...]]></description>
            <link>https://frodigo.com/Blog</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://frodigo.com/Blog</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Welcome in my blog. Below I listed all my articles from newest to oldest. You can also explore the blog using sidebar navigation. Enjoy!</p>
<h2>Software Architecture</h2>
<ul>
<li>[[Monolith vs Microservices - Pros and Cons and How to Approach Transformation]]</li>
<li>[[Hexagonal architecture (ports and adapters) - pros and cons]]</li>
</ul>
<h2>Cybersecurity</h2>
<ul>
<li>[[Historical cryptography algorithms]]</li>
</ul>
<h2>Tutorials</h2>
<ul>
<li>[[Caesar Cipher Implementation in C Sharp]]</li>
</ul>
<h2>Frontend</h2>
<ul>
<li>[[Everything you need to know about CSS modules]]</li>
</ul>
<h3>GraphQL</h3>
<ul>
<li>[[How to use GraphQL mutations in React and Apollo Client]]</li>
<li>[[Introduction to the Apollo local state and reactive variables]]</li>
<li>[[How to create a quick search component using Apollo lazy query]]</li>
<li>[[How to mock GraphQL queries and mutations]]</li>
<li>[[The full-stack guide to the GraphQL query]]</li>
<li>[[2 ways of handling GraphQL errors in Apollo Client]]</li>
</ul>
<h3>React</h3>
<ul>
<li>[[How to get started with routing in React apps with React Router]]</li>
<li>[[React Context API - It&#39;s Not as Difficult as You Think]]</li>
<li>[[What is react redux, and what development of redux apps looks in 2021]]</li>
<li>[[What is JSX in React, and is it worth making friends with it]]</li>
</ul>
<h3>Vue</h3>
<ul>
<li>[[Vue component here, Vue components there. Components everywhere!]]</li>
<li>[[How to get started with Vue (part1)]]</li>
</ul>
<h2>Magento</h2>
<ul>
<li>[[How to build a high-quality PWA Studio extensio]]</li>
<li>[[10 Answers to Your Questions About Magento Enterprise Versions]]</li>
<li>[[How to import Magento GraphQL schema to Postman]]]]</li>
<li>[[Magento 2 product types]]</li>
<li>[[Magento GraphQL - How to resolve URL]]</li>
<li>[[Magento graphql overview and how to get started in 2022]]</li>
<li>[[What is the difference between PWA Studio and the current Magento frontend]]</li>
<li>[[Getting started with Magento PWA Studio targetables]]</li>
<li>[[How to add support for Category Landing Pages to PWA Studio]]</li>
<li>[[How to extend PWA Studio with new features]]</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Books]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>Here I list books I read and used in my learning journey.</p>
<h2>Cryptography</h2>
<ul>
<li>[[Cryptography and network security principles and practice (fifth edition) by William Stallings]]</li>
</ul>
...]]></description>
            <link>https://frodigo.com/Books</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://frodigo.com/Books</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Here I list books I read and used in my learning journey.</p>
<h2>Cryptography</h2>
<ul>
<li>[[Cryptography and network security principles and practice (fifth edition) by William Stallings]]</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Contact]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<h3>My email</h3>
<p><a href="mailto:marcin@frodigo.com">marcin@frodigo.com</a></p>
<hr>
<h2>Social media</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/frodigo/" title="LinkedIn">Linkedin</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/Frodigo" title="GitHub">GitHub</a></li>
<li><a...]]></description>
            <link>https://frodigo.com/Contact</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://frodigo.com/Contact</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h3>My email</h3>
<p><a href="mailto:marcin@frodigo.com">marcin@frodigo.com</a></p>
<hr>
<h2>Social media</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/frodigo/" title="LinkedIn">Linkedin</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/Frodigo" title="GitHub">GitHub</a></li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/@marcin_12725" title="Medium">Medium</a></li>
</ul>
<hr>
<h2>Newsletter</h2>
<p>If you want to be updated with my new content you can subscribe to my newsletter.</p>
<p><a href="https://marcinkwiatkowski.kit.com">Subscribe to the newsletter</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Home]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>Hello!</p>
<p>My name is Marcin Kwiatkowski.</p>
<p>I am a full-stack <strong>software engineer</strong>, based in <strong>Poland</strong>. I solve problems with code since 2013. Almost all of my career I was working in the eCommerce area where I specialized in Magento.</p>
<p...]]></description>
            <link>https://frodigo.com/Home</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://frodigo.com/Home</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Hello!</p>
<p>My name is Marcin Kwiatkowski.</p>
<p>I am a full-stack <strong>software engineer</strong>, based in <strong>Poland</strong>. I solve problems with code since 2013. Almost all of my career I was working in the eCommerce area where I specialized in Magento.</p>
<p>Recently, I joined Docplanner and I help to make healthcare more human.</p>
<p>Besides engineering, I write articles on my blog and on Medium. Outside work I am a father, a husband and a runner.</p>
<p>I’m glad you came to my website. I hope you find something for yourself here.</p>
<p>[[About|More about me]]</p>
<hr>
<h2>My recent work</h2>
<h3>Open source projects</h3>
<p>I was a contributor to Magento and PWA Studio, also I have worked as the leader of the team that created the integration of Alokai Storefront with Magento 2.</p>
<p><a href="https://alokai.com/pwa-for-magento">Checkout out Alokai Storefront for Magento 2</a></p>
<h3>Alokai Console</h3>
<p>As a technical leader and software architect, I was responsible for the development of the VSF Console product.</p>
<p><a href="https://alokai.com/product/console">Checkout out Alokai Console</a></p>
<hr>
<h2>Knowledge base</h2>
<p>From many years I have been working blog. Actually I experimented with different type of content. What I discovered in this journey? Writing technical articles and tutorials is my favorite type of writing.</p>
<p>Based on that, I write for people like me: engineers, programmers and learners.</p>
<p>[[Blog|Read my blog]]</p>
<p>But sometimes I want to write stories, or content that is doesn&#39;t strictly related with engineering. This type of writing you can find on my Medium blog.</p>
<p><a href="https://medium.com/@frodigo">Read my Medium</a></p>
<p>Besides articles, I am a notetaker. All notes related to enginering I publish here and I name this type of content as &quot;Manuals&quot;.</p>
<p>[[Manual|Read manuals]]</p>
<hr>
<h2>What do people say about me?</h2>
<p>Marcin is a significant part of the success of the Magento/Adobe community and our work with PWA Studio and Venia. Marcin delivered our essential desktop experience for PWA in early 2021, which addressed a top customer need. He is a regular contributor in our community and continues to create content and examples for others to get started, which is highly appreciated. Beyond the work itself, Marcin is always open to feedback and serves as a model for open source contribution. We&#39;re grateful for his help and support!</p>
<p><strong>Eric Erway, Group Product Manager, Adobe</strong></p>
<p>Working with Marcin was a delight, and I truly hope that this was only one in many more opportunities to come in the near future. He is a talented Frontend Engineer (with strong UX and programming things understanding) and inspirational Team Leader, always willing to take on any task or help others with theirs. He is also a great communicator, collaborator, and extremely passionate about what he is doing.</p>
<p><strong>Bartosz Picho, Engineering Director, Vaimo</strong></p>
<p>I highly recommend working with Marcin on architecture topics. Each meeting was filled to the brim with substantial knowledge. From each session, I also took away a handful of materials for review. I&#39;m definitely signing up for the second edition of Architecture with Marcin!</p>
<p><strong>Przemysław Korościk, Engineering Manager, Monogo</strong></p>
<p>I had the pleasure to work with Marcin, and he is pure talent both in terms of technical and soft skills. He is always a committed and trusted member of a team. He amazed me with his problem-solving attitude and how proactive he is. Marcin is constantly looking for new things to learn and bring new ideas to the project. If you are looking for a guy that can solve any problem on the frontend, Marcin is that guy!</p>
<p><strong>Cezary Olejarczyk CEO at Open Loyality</strong></p>
<hr>
<h2>Congratulations, you&#39;ve reached the end of the page</h2>
<p>Can I help you in any way?</p>
<p>If so, just <a href="mailto:marcin@frodigo.com">write me a message</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Manual]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>A place where I write down all the technical terms I come across along the way.</p>
<p>It&#39;s a quite new idea, so at the moment not much content is here, but it will grow!</p>
<p>Categories below are related to my master&#39;s degree studies.</p>
<h2>Categories</h2>
<ul>
<l...]]></description>
            <link>https://frodigo.com/Manual</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://frodigo.com/Manual</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A place where I write down all the technical terms I come across along the way.</p>
<p>It&#39;s a quite new idea, so at the moment not much content is here, but it will grow!</p>
<p>Categories below are related to my master&#39;s degree studies.</p>
<h2>Categories</h2>
<ul>
<li>[[Manual/Machine learning|Machine learning]]</li>
<li>[[Cybersecurity]]</li>
<li>[[Cryptography]]</li>
<li>[[Internet of things]]</li>
<li>[[Math]]</li>
<li>[[Database Systems and MySQL]]</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Now]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>This is a <a href="https://nownownow.com/about">now</a> page, and if you have your own site, you <del>should</del> can make one, too.</p>
<p>Updated March 25, 2025 from Brzezina, Poland</p>
<hr>
<h2>Teaching My Son to Program</h2>
<p>I wanted to teach my son how to write code....]]></description>
            <link>https://frodigo.com/Now</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://frodigo.com/Now</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This is a <a href="https://nownownow.com/about">now</a> page, and if you have your own site, you <del>should</del> can make one, too.</p>
<p>Updated March 25, 2025 from Brzezina, Poland</p>
<hr>
<h2>Teaching My Son to Program</h2>
<p>I wanted to teach my son how to write code. What I did so far was not interesting to him too much. Actually it was boring. But I don&#39;t give up (yet).  </p>
<hr>
<h2>Decluttering</h2>
<p>At the end of last year I did an experiment with decluttering and I was happy with the results. I want to go a little further with this and do a total decluttering of both my digital and physical space, which involves getting rid of unnecessary things like subscriptions (detooling) on ​​the one hand and things I don&#39;t use on the other.</p>
<hr>
<h2>Master&#39;s degree studies</h2>
<p>About 10 years ago I finished my engineering studies and then I couldn&#39;t continue and go to master&#39;s studies. Now I can and I started studies in &quot;Artificial Intelligence and Machine Learning&quot;.</p>
<hr>
<h2>Garage project</h2>
<p>I love open source and also I enjoy learning and do experiments.</p>
<p>So far I pushed my experiments on my local computer, or on private GitHub repositories.</p>
<p>But I realized that I can connect my love to open source projects and experiments by creating one public project where I keep all my code and notes.</p>
<p>This is how the <a href="https://github.com/Frodigo/garage">garage</a> project is started.  </p>
<hr>
<h2>Describe AI usage in my project and website</h2>
<p>In last 2 years I experimented a lot with AI tools. To be honest with my readers</p>
<p>I want to describe how I use AI. I want to create something like <a href="https://www.bydamo.la/p/ai-manifesto">this</a></p>
<hr>
<h2>Removing multi-language support from my website</h2>
<p>I tried to write content in Polish and English, but it&#39;s time consuming.</p>
<p>I will use my time to do more experiments than translating content.</p>
<p>Because of that I decided that I will continue writing only in English and</p>
<p>I will remove all Polish content and code responsible for rendering it from my blog.</p>
<hr>
<h2>History</h2>
<p>Below you can find my historical now pages. Date along the title means a day when a page was moved to the history.</p>
<ul>
<li>[[25-03-2025]]</li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Privacy policy]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>This website doesn&#39;t use cookies. I do not track you or collect any information about you.</p>
<p>Happy reading!</p>
...]]></description>
            <link>https://frodigo.com/Privacy policy</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="false">https://frodigo.com/Privacy policy</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This website doesn&#39;t use cookies. I do not track you or collect any information about you.</p>
<p>Happy reading!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>